hey guys sh side welcome to concept and
coding and today we are going to start
the part two of spring boot security so
in the part one we have already seen
about architecture
right and we have to start understanding
about the authentication method like
form login basic authentication JWT O So
before we start all this authentication
method we have to first understand it's
the first step you can say the user
creation right why
because before we proceed with user
authentication and authorization like we
have to first create the user right so
that's this is the first step we can't
skip it right we can't directly jump to
the authentication method where we are
authorizing user and uh authenticate
user but first we have to create a user
right so we have to first understand
what is the best way or you can say that
the production level if you have to uh
create a user how it should be so let's
see that let's start that so yeah the
first line says that authentication and
authorization of user will happen only
after user is created so that's where
this is we here we are that's why we are
uh learning about it so let let's see
that what will happen when we add below
security dependency as we see in the
architecture video we in the
architecture video I told you that right
we need to add this dependency uh for
adding the spring boot security filters
and all now let's say that we have added
it and if we start our application what
would be the behavior what would happen
so if you start the application and you
will see the logs I have just started
the server nothing else I have added the
dependency okay and I have started the
server so while starting the server if
you see the logs you will see one thing
is using generated security password
some password got created and there is
one more thing to consider this it says
that using in memory user detail
manager what exactly happened here what
does it mean
so what actually happening here is when
we are starting the server user is
created
automatically spring boot security
automatically create a user for us with
default username is user okay and it
creates a random
password okay it create a random
password which get printed here in the
logs okay so each each time server is
restarted new random password will get
generated okay each time server is
restarted a new password will get
generated and this like you username
would always be user and password would
be uh this is like a random every time
which would get printed
here
so how if you see this code this is the
spring framework code there there is a
class called Spring properties. Java
inside that there is a static user
class if you see it properly you will
see default username is
user password for the default username
is uu ID Universal unique identifier
some random uu ID it take it role is
empty okay so this is the first it
create that now after after that there
is a user details service autoc
configuration. Java there is some
configuration class which creates Bean
so that's one bean is present where is
creating an object of in memory user
detail
manager actually what it is doing is
this class uh this Bean it stores this
user and the password which we have got
the username is user and the password is
some random this one right somewhere it
has to be
stored okay so that's where this Bean
which it is calling in memory user
detail manager user details manager so
it is managing the user details user
detail is nothing but a username and
password and it is putting in memory so
ultimately it will store in some kind of
a in memory that okay this is the
username and this is the password later
on you can fetch it so here if you see
this in memory user detail manager what
it is doing is it the parameter it
accepted as a security properties this
one only okay from this it will get the
user so this is security property do
user this class so it has default
username default password now what it
does
is it creating an object of in memory
user detail manager and now now it is
converting from this user it is
converting to another user okay so it is
you can say that uh it is doing a
mapping so user do username it put a
username it put a password it put a
roles and it build it so once it get a
in memory user detail manager so what it
will do it will call its Constructor
right now here if you
see in memory user detail manager it's
Constructor
so it got this user details so this is
where it does doing a mapping right
security property. user it is mapping it
to user
details user details user details is an
interface and its implementation is I
think user okay
so here in the object Constructor of
this inmemory user detail manager it is
accepting this parent user details okay
and here it is actually uh creating an
uh object for this one user it is
creating a user object this one so with
username with password with roles it
read out the information from security
property. user to this one it fill it
and it calls new in memory user detail
manager ultimately it will call its
Constructor inside a Constructor what it
will calling create user now here if you
see create user how what it is doing it
is putting users dop put username and
here all the user
details and here if you see users this
is
final so you know that in a spring boot
each class by default is singl time and
this is the final so no matter how many
uh requests would come only one object
would be created so they will all share
this users map so that's where it is in
memory it is storing in memory so
whatever the user when you started the
server so username which is
user and the password
this ultimately it get stored into
inmemory inside
here okay that's where here you see that
in memory user detail manager who is
managing
this okay so fun thing is clear
right now one thing should comes to your
mind at this point of time hey like
random username uh like user and random
password it's okay for testing purpose
but again how I can control this so that
in product at least we can use it
because uh we we let's say that I want
to add a custom user name custom user
custom password I want to add it so
definitely this question would comes to
a mind that how can we control the user
creation logic instead of spring boot
creates a default username and password
for me okay so that's where different
approaches
come so this is the first approach using
application. properties again not
recommended only for development and
testing so in application. properties
you use this spring. security. user.name
you give whatever username you wanted to
give I give myor
username then spring. security. user.
password whatever the password you want
to give you can give it here and then
spring. security user. roles whatever
the roles you wanted to give give it
here so what actually it will do is
internally it will use
reflection and call set username and set
password method of security properties
and overwrite the default values so in
security
properties right it has a a name user
password random right and it also has
getter and Setter so ultimately spring
boot will call those Setter methods and
it will overwrite the name password and
roles you through
reflection and when you start an
application now you will see that no
default username and password is created
here if you see Server is
started and after
that you now you have a user whenever
you wanted uh login this is the user
username you can use this is the
password you can
use but again this is just
for development purpose it is not
recommended at all to use it
production but okay second thing is now
again before we move to the second part
what what give us a more Curious that we
have to go 2 second like first question
again comes to me is that okay what
if I want to
create more
than one
user what if I want to create more than
one
user then how to do it okay yeah we can
do that but through application do
properties only one you we can create
but if you have to create more than one
there is a second way also we can use
but with this
one we can you can say that uh we will
get lot more information we will
understand like how actually it's
internal working
also by creating the custom inmemory
user detail manager Be So currently if
you
see the default
Behavior first
here what happened
is security property. user object is
created which has default user and
password okay
then it tried
to create an object
of internal
memory user detail
manager and when it creates a object of
it it accept the user
detail the user which has username
password roles and ultimately it put
into the cache okay and in the 2.1 it
put
into
Cash okay so now here if you see that if
we have to create more than one user so
here if you see one thing the inmemory
user detail manager can accept more than
one
users so can we can we take the
responsibility of creating
a object of internal or not internal in
memory this is in memory can we take the
responsibility of creating an object of
in memory user detail manager if yes we
can create an object of it like instead
of this we can create and we can pass as
many users we
wanted okay we know that the user it
accept as the user details so we can
create as many users we wanted that's
what I am going to do
now so here if you see just to Showcase
that in memory user detail
manager it's a child of user detail
manager which is again a child of user
Detail
Service okay
so here I am writing one configuration
we already know how to write it we have
already seen that uh in previous
lectures I am creating one
bean now I am
creating and being of user details
service user details service why because
I don't want to put exact in memory user
detail manager you can do it but
generally it's always recommended that
use the parent one okay so in memory
user detail manager is a child of user
detail manager which again is a child of
user Detail Service so that's where I
using this and we know that in memory
user detail manager class right it
accept multiple user details you see
that three dots here so we can pass
multiple users to it okay and that's
what I am doing it so first I am
creating one user
details okay I passed the
username password roles and build it
similarly second and I I am now taking
the responsibility of creating its
object because I want it in memory right
now here I am creating a
specific object right this is just an
interface we can't create an object of
it this is the concrete class we can
create an object of it so here I am
creating an inmemory user detail and
passing more than one
object so now it will create two users
in the
map okay one with myor username one
another is mycore username 2 and
object where has complete information
about this
users
okay but again so it's like a chain like
of asking questions now you have seen
this
if you notice one thing in the password
I have
written no op and then given my password
my password one and here for the second
user I return no op and then give the
password 1 2 3 4 what does this know up
mean why I use it or what different
values it can take okay so now let's see
that the no op means that
no encoding no hashing in
this in memory or wherever the data like
currently we are storing in memory let's
say that if you want to store in DB no
matter what would be the storage point
no op means that the password is not
even encoded not even hashed it is like
in a plain
text plain text no hashing happened no
encoding happened
nothing okay so here the default format
for storing the password default I'm
saying the default format for storing
the password is like
this ID like this ID and your encoded
password here above I uses no
of so this become my ID and you're
encoded password so no op means that not
even encoded not even has so just plain
text so 1 2 3 4 is my
password okay
but apart from no op we can also use if
you want to do a oneway hashing very
secure we can use bcrypt or if you want
to use sha 256 algorithm you can use
that
also okay so there are multiple you can
say that hashing algorithms present
which we can use
it okay
so now what how exactly this work we
also need to understand right we know
that okay the default format for storing
the password anywhere is this but how
why how come is this working like why
why I need to put before my
password okay so see the flow understand
the
flow I will tell you example but first
read this three lines what would happen
during let's say user password storing a
step we are storing the let's say in a
in memory or DB we are restoring the
user detail username and the object
complete object where it has username
password role
everything we want to store user
password without any encoding or hashing
then we know that we have to use this ID
no op and we have to store like this no
op what 1 2 3 4 plain
password now what would happen during so
let's say that I have stored it just for
a one moment assume that I have stored
like this in a DB or in memory now
during authentication process what will
happen during authent now this is stored
in your DB now you are trying to
authenticate user user is providing its
username hey my username is username
uncore 1 my password is 1 2 3 4 user
will not pass no no op right it will
just say that plain like my password is
1 2 3 4 so during authentication process
what would happen is step one it will
Spring boot
framework fet the user password from
inmemory based on this username it will
let's say check its in memory or DB it
know that okay this is the username it
will fetch out the object where it has a
password let's say password is stored
like this we have stored like this
second it now has to compare what the
user has provided to us 1 2 3 4 and what
we have already stored correct so it
goes for the comparing logic but before
comparing the third step is it will
first read
out what is the ID so here it is say
that no op now spring boot knows that
okay no op means that whatever
the password is stored it is not even
encrypted not even hash so it has to
directly compare what is coming from
user directly coming what is uh user is
sending but let's say that for a second
if in memory or DB it is
this
bcrypt and let's say that a b c 1 2 3
some in the hash form it has a stored
now user is passing 1 2 3
4 so how the spring framework knows that
how to compare this two so what it will
do is first it will read out this ID now
it will uh separate this one one is
bcrypt and now it has a b c 1 2 3 now it
knows that okay the password which I
have stored in my DB or in memory is
hashed form and it is hashed via bcrypt
algorithm now what it will do is that
whatever the password which user is
passing it will also hash it using
bcrypt and whatever
the output comes then only it will
compare
it
okay so that's how
the ID is stored or you can say that
that's how the format for storing the
password is like this okay so this is
the step now here if you see in the
password
encoder this is the default password
encoder delegating password encoder this
is the
default it work is to delegate to other
password encoder based on
ID okay so we we have different uh
password encoder like BP noop there
could be other sha 256 password encoder
different but the first if you're not
using directly like hey I want use this
if you're not telling specifically what
it will do is Spring Security framework
first pass this to delegate password
encoder this password encoder work is
that whatever the password we have
stored it first try to look for the ID
and based on that ID it will delegate to
a appropriate
encoder okay
so that's why I am passing the password
like this
here I hope that's clear but again it's
a chain right of a question let's say if
you want to store the hash part
password then how you would do that
just see
that again I am creating a
bean
okay Bean of user Detail Service this is
an interface ultimately I'm creating an
object of a concrete class in memory
user detail manager I am passing it at
one user details object I am creating it
username password role and building it
now here if you see the password I am
how I am storing it as bcrypt first I
I've added the ID and then using this
encoder and I'm encoding it my plain
password okay and ultimately in DB it
will be stored in a hashed
format now even if user passes 1 2 3 4
Spring Security framework will take out
it will goes to delegating password
encoder
first okay and delegating password
encoder will
uh take out this ID it will know that
okay uh this is
the password encoder which I have used
and then ultimately it will pass to that
particular encoder to do a uh like
whatever the user has passord right 1 2
3 4 it will first do encoding using this
and then ultimately match it because
this is Hash right one way it can't just
uh change again back to like what what I
have provided my password one it's a one
way uh you can say the hashing is one
way whatever the like a b c XY Z do 21 2
three so it's a oneway uh hashing so
whatever the user passed only that can
again be hashed and then compare those
two
hash
okay so just here see an example that I
have shown an example I am giving
username
one and I am giving the password the
password I am giving like
this okay so here if you see username
and the password plain password I'm
giving but still I'm able to
authenticate and properly able to access
the
API why because even though I have
stored in the DB in the in uh hashed
form why I told you right it first hash
this
also okay but by which algorithm
that delegating password encoder will
decide based on the ID and it will pass
it so first whatever the password which
I'm passing it will hash it and then
match it and if it get matched I will
get
access now again one question should
comes to your mind Hey sh if you don't
want to store bcrypt or any other
hashing go in front of password this
doesn't look good like if somebody is
checking my DB or in memory if password
like it says that bcrypt and then some
password no op some password or
something s256 some password I don't
want to store in that way like is there
any way we can do that yes we can do
that so currently I told you the by
default spring boot use delegating
password password encoder because spring
doesn't know which password encoder to
use okay whatever the password you have
used while defining it will go to that
encoder but if you specify the one
encoder to Spring Security it will
directly goes to that encoder itself it
won't goes to delegation so we don't
want to store it so that's what I am
doing it so in the same configuration
now I just added one more Bean for
password
encoder okay I am just creating this is
an interface password encoder is an
interface I'm just saying that Hey
whenever password encoder is
used always create an object of bcrypt
password encoder I always need
bcrypt and if you see now when I'm
creating a user I created a usern name
now the password I don't need to put at
theate bcrypt it's not required because
whenever any encoding uh or hashing is
required or whenever the user will enter
a password 1 2 3 4 automatically request
will goes to the password encoder no
matter what it will get hashed and then
only it will get
compare okay because I have specifically
mentioned I am using this password
encoder got the
difference but again one question comes
to your mind that
okay I got it how I can create multiple
users in my system okay and various
password encoder and the flow but still
this is not recommended for production
like in production I can't have this uh
default username and password okay and
also in production I can't store the
details in in memory I have to store in
DB right first thing is I have to stor
in DB and in DB my password should be
hashed properly correct and it should be
dynamic I should not have stored a
static username and
password that's where the third approach
or you can say the Third Way of creating
a user comes in and which is recommended
for
production okay based on my
understanding so
if you if you understand this basic
flow this
one what we are
doing
then it's very easy to write a code for
this one the one we are going to see uh
DB approach just see here that what I'm
doing the first first
is I am creating my own entity because
now I want to store in a DB I want to
take a control like what the data should
go into my DB so I am creating one
entity user o entity. Java okay it's an
entity the table name I have given as
user and I have making it as a child of
user detail why I would tell you
but for the first step just say that I
have created an
entity okay where I have like ID
username password
roles okay so this four columns I
required okay there are
certain here if you see override comes
in that is because we have I am
implementing this user detail
interface now you can ask me that hey
okay I understand that we want to store
the username and password in DB for that
we are creating a table but why we have
to implement this user details what is
the requirement for that one
so before that one let me tell you that
what happened first the step
is user
created okay when the user is created
let's say in DB or in
memory we have
username and we have
password okay that's the first step
second step is
authentication where we are using let's
say form or basic or
JWT so now all this authentication
method what we do is we have
to fetch the first step is fast the
user we have to F the user right
and this user we have to fetches like uh
spring framework goes and fetch so it
will goes and fetch whether it's a DB or
in memory wherever the user we are
storing
it it has to fast the user okay and once
it is f the
user the return type of this is user
details okay and the same thing if you
see
it
here in memory where we are restoring it
we are restoring it the user the user is
nothing an object of user
details okay so here it's that's why so
we have to be consistent what we
actually wanted to store in our DB also
right so that's way it become easy that
we have a we don't have to do mapping
like what we are getting and what uh
spring boot required I can
directly use user authentity I don't
have to do a mapping like whatever the
data I am getting from user authentity I
have to map it to user Detail no since
user authentity I make it as a child of
user
detail okay so during framework a spring
framework wherever it is required user
details right if I am returning user
authentity it will work and you will
understand soon but for this is what I
have written
here because during authentication
different method security framework try
to F the user and return the object of
user detail only if you don't implement
it if we don't implement it then we have
to do the mapping from user authentity
to user detail I will show you the place
where we have to do the mapping
also okay so now here if you see that we
have to override all these things like
is account not expired is account not
logged credential not expired currently
I have default return true yes not
expired not loged everything is good but
in production we have to give a specific
implementation maybe you will need to
require more columns Also let's say
account not expired your company la
logic would be that uh account not
expired logic B should be based on date
okay uh current uh date password is
stored okay and uh it should not if it
is more than 90 days then it is like
let's say I have to say expired so you
might be storing date also and here you
will write a comparing logic between
current date and the date uh the
password is stored and see if it is more
than 90 days you return password expire
ired true or if it is not expired return
false something like that I hope you got
it so
this all these methods returns or you
can say
that you can implement this logic based
on the custom logic which you want or
custom requirement you can add more
columns based on that you can write a
logic on this is account is logged or
not credential expired or not like this
but
the one thing is we have to create an
entity like what all columns we required
in a DB and that's where what I have
created it and I have created a child of
user details which I have told you
why the second is created a repository
for this entity we have to create a
repository again we have already seen
this jpa repository and they have return
return one method find by username you
already know that in the previous video
in the JP I've already told you how this
worked the spring boot would
automatically create a query for me
because find by it sees that right so it
will automatically create a uh select
query for me where it will put username
equals to
this so I have written find by
username now here if you see the third I
have to I have written one service class
user or entity service class and now
here if you see notice also I have
implemented it user Detail
Service you might ask again why again if
you see the flow
during user creation you don't need it
user creation you don't need it in user
creation we store in DB or in memory
username
password but during authentication it is
required in future it might require
during Authentication
framework first try to
fetch the
user
from DB or in
memory for in memory it knows how to
fetch it but for DB it don't know how to
fetch it which table it I have to fetch
it from so we have created the
table and we have written that okay uh
in this service class I am writing this
method which ultimately fet the detail
but how spring framework knows that like
I have to use this method so that's
where I am implementing user Detail
Service you know right user Detail
Service then we have user detail manager
and then we have in memory user detail
manager so we have seen that right user
Detail Service which is the parent uh
interface and then we have user detail
manager and at the bottom we have in
memory user detail manager so now I am
creating that hey I am creating one more
service which
is user
o and user o entity service or user o
service something I am creating this
class okay and whenever you have to F
the user you don't have to go to
inmemory you can comes to me user
authentity manager that's why I have
created a child of user Det manager so I
have keep keep it in parallel to in
memory okay and it has to overwrite this
method so that the spring framework
because spring framework already calling
this one load user by username so now
ultimately since we have implemented it
this method will get
invoke so now load user by username and
uh we know that how to fetch it we have
our repository we will use it repository
and we call find by username and we will
return it now here if you see that I
what I am returning user
authentity I am not returning user
details okay I am not returning so here
if you
see in memory user detail
manager okay so there would be um just
go to
here this is the parent
interface I am implementing this
load user by
username what is the return type user
details okay and this is what spring
Frameworks invo it to F the username
during authentication I'm saying during
authentication not during storing during
authentication it first has to F the
data from DB or n memory right so it
will call
this now the return type is user detail
if I have not implemented this if I have
not done
this then would I be able to return just
user authentity no then first I have to
do
mapping what I would received as a user
o entity to user details object and then
returns user
details but since I have created as a
child Implement user details that's why
I am directly returning this and it is
acceptable
now
okay okay so what till now what we have
done is we have created an table where
we are going to store the username
password we have created a repository
and we are creating a service class okay
because spring boot during
authentication might not know how to fet
from the DB it knows how to F from in
memory but for DB don't know how to
fetch it so we are telling we are
writing implementing this load by
username we are fetching it from which
table we have to fetch and we are
returning
it all
good now we can just write controller
last step so now here if you see I am
writing this
sl/ register
API
okay user can give username password now
what I'm doing is before even storing
into the DB before I'm calling this
service. save class save method
this I
am hashing the
password so I am using password encoder
do
encode user details. getet password so
what it will do is it will encod
whatever the user is sending me the
plain password right so I'm getting that
plain
password and encode it
okay like whatever the algorithm which
we will decide and using that algorithm
it will now update the password here in
the same object and then ultimately I'm
going to store
it okay and which encoder we have to use
we can tell into our Spring Security
configuration I have told
that I want to use bcrypt password
encoder so it will use that encoder and
encode my pass password and override
whatever the plane password user is
passing and then I will save
it right
now one last question should have comes
to you that
okay Shan this
API o and register at this API we are
saying that user can
dynamically add their
username and password okay and we will
store it in
DB we will store it into DB okay but how
user would be able to invoke it by
default in Spring Security each and
every API is authenticated means for
each API you have to provide a username
and
password but this is the first step
itself where we are creating the
username password itself we don't have
username password yes to authenticate it
so what to do we have to bypass the
authentication for this API so in the
same if you
see there is a security filter chain I
will come into more depth when we start
the authentication methods okay so
different security filter chain comes so
we will override so now here if you see
I am saying that request any request
which matches this/ or/ register permit
don't do any
authentication apart from any request
authenticated so what ultimately I I'm
doing is I am bypassing or you can say
that skipping this API sl/
register right uh no authentication
would be executed for it apart from it
for rest of the apis authentication is
required and this is industry
standard okay so when this API is got
invol
username would be stored let's say U1
password would be stored in the bcrypt
format let's say XY Z 1 2 3 something
roles would be stored what would be
given like this and some
ID okay and during when authentication
happens any authentication
happens spring framework we will see the
flow but the spring framework first has
to fetch this username right we have
provided it it
like spring Frameworks we have provided
like uh overrided this user Detail
Service so ultimately this method would
get invoked this method will goes to
user or entity repository it knows that
how to fetch it from user authentity
from this okay and it will return
it
simple okay so I hope this is clear and
uh we can see that Also let's
see so in this one I have skipped the Au
register part I am starting the
server
okay let's say that I'm trying to login
but there is no user present currently
let's say U1 1 2 3 does any such user
exist no so we are creating like
U1 1 2 3 let's say this is the same
username password I wanted to create
first I send it like user registered
successfully I am no authentication
required for Au register API now I am
providing here again U1 1 2 3 sign in
now I am able to
login okay so and if you check the DB in
DB you can see that the password is
stored like
this see dollar 2 a and all this thing
how in the bcrypt encoding hash manner
it is stored but I hope user creation
process is clear and even if somebody
ask like uh what's the recommended way
to create a user in uh production I
think we now I have the answer also okay
guys any doubt we can discuss more but
thank you very much bye